building a real-time application can be very
tricky and it often requires you to store data
in multiple different formats but did you know
redis stack makes redis a multi-model database
and supports many of the capabilities
you need all in a single database
thus saving you time and reducing complexity when
trying to use databases from several providers
i built a sample application here that is for
tracking a stock watch list under the hood it
stores data in several different ways using redis
stack as the primary database and message broker
not only am i using some basic data
types like sets and hashes but i'm
also storing json documents time series
data and even some probabilistic data
i'm also using pub sub to communicate information
between a few different micro services in real
time more on that later though for now let's dive
into what you're looking at the main focus of
this app is the watch list you can see here that
i'm watching a number of popular stock symbols
i can even search for more if i want to so i just
go in and i type in bac and you can see several
different stock tickers here and i can add those
to my watch list if i need to just by clicking on
them i can also remove them if i want to from
here and on the right hand side of this card
you can see the real-time trading information
so you'll see the latest trade from each stock
on the right hand side of the page you'll see
this card called trending stocks which displays a
list of most frequently traded stocks in my watch
list over the last minute every minute it resets
and keeps track of the number of trades that
happen within that minute the bottom of the
page shows information based on what stock you
select in your watch list so you can click on
different symbols in the watch list to change the
information that's displayed the chart is updated
in real time using the alpaca api the number in
the top left of the chart shows the latest trade
price as well as the delta between the latest
trade and the previous minute closing price
every minute i receive a new closing
price from alpaca and update this chart
on the right hand side you see recent news
this is news that's grabbed from the alpaca api
about the particular stock you're looking at now
let's break down how i'm storing retrieving and
managing the data used to populate this screen
the watch list is stored in redis as a set
a set makes the most sense for this case since
it automatically prevents any duplicate symbols
i'm also storing information about each stock
such as the name sector industry and a list of
news in a json document in redis stack the price
is stored in a time series using the time series
capabilities of redis stack this makes it easy to
get the latest price very quickly when the front
end requests the watch list i bring down some of
the information from the json document as well as
the latest trade for each symbol in the list then
i'm using a websocket to receive price updates
the trend list uses a top k filter which is a
feature built into redis stack that automatically
builds a leaderboard for you as trades come in
from the alpaca api i simply add them to the top
k filter and it lets me know if the leaderboard
has changed the chart uses time series data
retrieved in real time from the alpaca api
and stored in redis stack as a time series
when you store time series data in redis stack
it makes it very easy for you to query the data
over a date range as well as aggregate the data
it's perfect for storing data that you want to
visualize on a chart where time is on the x-axis
the news list is kept up to date using the alpaca
api and is stored in a json document in redis
stack along with other information about a stock
so you can see that while this app might look
simple on the front end behind the scenes there's
a lot going on and the entire thing is powered
by redis stack now let's look at an architecture
diagram for this application so you can get a
sense of how all the pieces fit together looking
at this architecture diagram we'll start over on
the left with the front end the front end which is
what we just looked at is responsible for getting
all the data needed to populate that dashboard
so that's the time series information to populate
the chart and the most up-to-date stock prices
it also populates the watch list it also gets
the trending stocks and it gets the news about
the stocks you're interested in what it also
does is it uses a websocket with the api service
to get real-time updates on stock prices news and
the trending stocks next we have the api service
so the api service is relatively simple it just
facilitates communication between the front end
and redis stack it updates the watch list when
you add or remove a stock from the watch list
on the front end and it queries for the data
needed to populate the front end so all that
data we just talked about the watch list the
leaderboard the time series data and the news
it also receives pub sub messages with
all the leaderboard updates new trades
and new bars which are the open and closed prices
for a stock it receives those directly from redis
and those are actually generated those messages
are generated by the streaming service so what
the streaming service does is it communicates
with the alpaca api to receive real-time news
trade information bars and quotes and when it
receives a new quote or a trade it will update the
leaderboard using redis bloom and the top k filter
then it publishes updates using pub sub with redis
for leaderboard changes or whenever there's a new
trade or a new bar available it also subscribes
to watch list updates so on the front end when you
add a stock to the watch list the api is going to
send a message to redis saying update the watch
list and the streaming service will receive that
message and automatically subscribe to updates
from the alpaca api for that particular stock
every time a new trade or bar or quote or news
comes into the streaming service from alpaca
it adds it to the time series for the stocks in
the watch list so what you can essentially see
here is that redis is handling a lot of what you
might otherwise use several other tools to do so
it not only does it let you store data in multiple
different formats but redistac also lets you use
pub sub to communicate between microservices i'm
sure by now you're itching to look at some code to
understand how the application is built instead
of showing you all the code which could take
several hours to go through in depth i'm going to
highlight some specific areas that are interesting
if you're interested in learning more you can find
the code in the description down below this video
looking at the code you can see i have an api
service a stream service and a ui service the
ui service is for the front end that we were just
looking at i'm not going to show you too much of
the front end code because it's fairly similar
to other applications you may have built but i
will mention that it's using tailwind css chart.js
and nexjs so it's a very typical front-end next.js
application that just calls an api to get all
the data but let's look at what the api looks
like i wrote the api using python and fast api as
well as redisome for communicating with redistac
so the first two routes here are for the watch
list it lets you watch and unwatch stocks
so add and remove stocks from your watch list i'm
using a redis set to keep track of your watch list
this makes it really easy because you can
automatically avoid duplicates the next route
is to just get the watch list what it does is
it grabs the set out of redis and then it uses
redis ohm to get all the json documents where the
symbol for the json document is in my watch list
this lets me bring more information forward such
as the news and some other information about the
stock another route is searching so this uses
redissearch to find stocks so when you're typing
in the form in your watch list on the front
end as soon as you get to a certain number
of characters i start searching for stock symbols
this uses redis search and redisown this route is
for getting all the bars over the last 30 minutes
so what i mean by bar is the alpaca api gives you
what's called bars that have a high price a low
price a volume an open price and a close price
within a certain time period so i'm looking at the
last 30 minutes of bars and this route just simply
you provide a stock symbol and it returns the bars
for you the next route gives you an individual
trade so it will give you the latest trade for
a particular symbol and the price of that trade
both of these routes are using redis time series
which is part of redis stack and it stores time
series data so that you can easily query it
over a range kind of like we're doing here
or get the latest value which is what we're doing
here this is the trending route so this will give
us the list of trending stocks remember those
stocks are trending based on the trading frequency
so all this does is looks at the top k filter
and asks it to give us the list this is using
redis bloom which is part of redis stack now
the next few things might look like routes but
they're actually web sockets so i have a trending
stock websocket here where the front end can say
hey give me all updates about trending stocks and
this will just listen to redis stack for messages
about the trending stocks and automatically
inform you that there's an updated trending list
this next one is similar but for trades so
it lets you know whenever there's a new trade
and then the last one is for bars so it
will let you know when there's new bars
on the front end this is how we update all of
the price information in the watch list and this
is how we update the graph that's about it for
the api let's look at the streaming service now
the first thing we want to look at for the
streaming service is the entry point which
is the main.pi so that like the api this is
written in python and it uses the alpaca sdk
as well as redis stack in the main loop all
that we're doing is connecting to alpaca
deleting the trending stocks so the training
stocks key is what we use to keep track of the
trending stocks using redis bloom and top k then
it reserves the training stocks again and syncs up
the watch list with whatever is in the set in
redis at that time what reserve top k does is
it just reserves this key to be used with the top
k filter and we're saying keep track of the 12
most frequently traded stocks and then we also
set an expiration of this key to 60 seconds
the reason for this is every 60 seconds we rebuild
the training stock list so on the front end
every 60 seconds you can see okay what stocks are
being actively traded so this is where we're using
pub sub to understand when the training stocks
key has expired and whenever it's expired we
re-reserve it and start rebuilding the list we're
also listening to the watch list so if you recall
in the api on the front end you can add something
to your watch list or remove it when you do that
the api simply updates the set within redis well
here we're going to be listening to that watchlist
key space and whenever it updates we will sync
it so let's dive into what that looks like here
when we sync the watch list we're basically
getting the watch list doing a set comparison and
unsubscribing from anything we need to unsubscribe
from and subscribing to whatever we need to
subscribe to the rest of this is all alpaca
related so we call subscribe trades these are
how we listen to the alpaca api in real time and
get trades as well as bars we can also initialize
a stock if we need to and what this will do is it
will give us historical trades and historical bars
about the stock and it'll also create the time
series keys that we need in redis stack so here
it's creating all the time series with all the
trades over the last whatever time period we
decided which i think i decided the time period
was going to be the last 30 minutes or something
and that's about it in here the next piece of
this is what happens as incoming trades and
incoming bars come in as incoming trades come
in we add the trade to our time series and then
we also add it to our top k and then we publish an
update saying okay the top we've updated the top k
so there are is a new trade in the top k that will
tell our api to update the top k list on the front
end and if you remember there's a websocket that
the front end can listen to to get updates to
those trending stocks so message flow here is an
incoming trade comes from alpaca then we publish
a message saying okay we've updated the trades
and updated the trending stocks list then the api
receives that message and it will notify the front
end if there are any changes needed and i've just
shown you just a little sneak peek of all the
code that is in here i wanted to show you some
specific things to have you get a sense of how all
of the pieces fit together within this application
but the next thing i want to show you is how this
looks in redis insight in redis insight you can
see how we have a bunch of json documents that
represent each stock so i pulled a bunch of data
from nasdaq directly to populate all this
information let's look at the watch list
so the watch list is a set and you can
see it has all the items that are on
that were represented on our
watch list on the front end
so this is how we're able to keep track of what
we're watching and add and remove things from
this set when we either don't want to watch them
anymore or with if we want to watch a new stock
now let's look at something on our watch
list so like apple so if i filter to apple
you'll see we have a bunch of different data
structures for apple itself the first one
is this json document so it stores information
such as the market cap the name apple common stock
the sector and the industry it also has an
embedded list of news articles so this is
where on the front end we're showing you all those
list of articles and then we let you click and go
to them this is what we're pulling from the alpaca
api so as new news articles come in we update this
json document with the article we're also storing
a bunch of different time series related to quotes
trades and bars you can't see the data in this
but let's look at what it looks like to get the
latest trade from apple so what we'll do is we'll
use the ts.get command to get the latest price of
the apple trade so the first value that's returned
is the timestamp and the second one is the price
and what we do is we query this over a range
in order to populate the chart on the front end
the command for that is ts.range and what i'll
do here is specify a from time stamp and a two
time stamp to get several different values so on
the front end we get a list of key value pairs
where the key is the timestamp and the value is
the stock price so hopefully by now you get a
sense of how powerful redis stack is and how it
turns redis into a multi-model database that you
can use to replace several technologies that you
would typically use in a real-time application
here our entire application from start
to finish is powered by redis stack